Guide to the Eve Arnold Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Eve Arnold papers
1950-2005
YCAL MSS 611
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
88.9
195 boxes + 6 rolls + 4 film reels
The Eve Arnold Papers contains her photographs, contact sheets, negatives, slides, transparencies, diaries, film production files, correspondence, writings by and about Arnold, printed materials, and ephemera that document her career as a member of the Magnum Photos cooperative. In addition, the collection contains audiovisual materials including motion picture film, videocassettes, sound recordings, and computer media.
Arnold, Eve
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Eve Arnold on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund and the Arthur Corbitt Hoskins Memorial Fund, 2003-2006.
Custodial History
The collection was packed and shipped from Arnold's studio in London; it retains her original order and enclosures, including her negative sleeves, her slide and publicity binders, and in some cases, photographs stored in commercial photo paper boxes.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 57-59 (sound recordings): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 60-66, 134 and 204(audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 68-71 (motion picture film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 72 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Eve Arnold (1912-2012)
Eve Arnold, American photographer and photojournalist, was born in Philadelphia on April 21, 1912, the daughter of Russian immigrants William and Bessie Cohen. While in her late 20s she moved to New York, where she took a job in a Hoboken photo-finishing plant, married industrial designer Arnold Arnold, and began making her own photographs. Her formal education in photography consisted of a six-week course taught by Alexey Brodovitch at the New School for Social Research in 1947. Her only child, Francis, was born in 1948.
Eve Arnold joined with Magnum Photos in 1951; she became an associate member of the photographers' collective in 1955, and in 1957 its first female full member in New York. The organization, founded in 1947 by Robert Capa, Henri Cartier-Bresson, George Rodger, and David "Chim" Seymour, followed Cartier-Bresson's dictum that "one must stay photographically in contact with the realities taking place in front of our lenses and not hesitate to sacrifice material comfort and security." In her work, Arnold traveled to document events, politics, personalities, society, and material culture in locations including Afghanistan, Africa, Cuba and the Caribbean, India, Europe, Egypt, the Soviet Union/Russia, the United Arab Emirates, and Yugoslavia, as well as the United States and the United Kingdom. She was also known for her documentation of American celebrity culture through her images of film stars Marilyn Monroe, Marlene Dietrich, Joan Crawford, and others at work, play, and home; she was the photographer on more than 35 movie sets, most notably The Misfits, a 1961 American drama directed by John Huston from a screenplay by Arthur Miller, which was the last film made by both actors Marilyn Monroe and Clark Gable. Arnold also photographed groups as diverse as the 1952 American Republican National Convention, Malcolm X and his Muslim followers, and Mikhail Baryshnikov and the American Ballet Theatre dancers. Her work was regularly published in popular magazines, specialized periodicals, and a variety of books during her lifetime, and was featured in one-woman shows and group exhibitions in the United States and Great Britain; she received honorary degrees from the University of St. Andrews and the University of Sheffield. Arnold wrote or co-authored more than a dozen books including The Unretouched Woman (1976), Flashback! the 50's (1978), In China (1980), In America (1983), Marilyn Monroe, an Appreciation (1987), Private View: Inside Baryshnikov's American Ballet Theatre (1988), All in a Day's Work (1989), The Great British (1991), Film Journal (2002), and Handbook (with footnotes) (2004), in addition to her autobiographical volume Eve Arnold: In Retrospect (1995). She also produced and directed a film, Behind the Veil (1972), which examined harem life in eastern Arabia.
Eve Arnold moved to London in 1961 with her son Francis, and remained a resident of that city until her death there on January 5, 2012. Further biographical information can be found in the Photographers section of the Magnum Photos website, http://www.magnumphotos.com.
Scope and Contents
The Eve Arnold Papers contains her photographs, negatives, slides, contact sheets, transparencies, diaries, film production files, writings by and about Arnold, printed materials, correspondence, and ephemera that document her career as a member of the Magnum Photos cooperative. In addition, the collection contains audiovisual materials including motion picture film, videocassettes, sound recordings, and computer media.
In this guide, dates assigned to photographs reflect the date of the original negative/story/job, as assigned by Arnold, and not necessarily the date of the actual photograph or contact sheet present in the collection. In many cases they may be the same, but Arnold and her contract printers continued to print from her negatives for many years in support of her exhibitions and publications. While the main sequence of negatives and contact sheets appears in group II of her papers, Arnold's exhibition and publication projects resulted in the dispersal of many negatives and contact sheets throughout the four acquisitions of material comprising the collection. In addition, other materials related to specific projects are also dispersed throughout the four groups. Arnold's chronology-based "story numbers" are referred to throughout the collection; her "story list" is filed in box 137.
As information in this collection guide was obtained from folder and other labels assigned by Arnold or her staff, note that their terminology is in some cases inconsistent; for instance, images made in the United Kingdom may be filed alphabetically under Britain, Great Britain, or U.K.
Arrangement
Organized into four groupings: I. June 2003 Acquisition. II. August 2004 Acquisition. III. June 2005 Acquisition. IV. June 2006 Acquisition.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time. Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with/or relates to material found in other acquisitions. For instance, photographic material can be found in all four groupings. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section. Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
Celebrities -- Pictorial works; Motion picture actors and actresses -- United States -- Pictorial works; Photographers -- United States; Photojournalism; Portrait photography; Women -- Middle East -- Pictorial works; Women photographers -- United States; Afghanistan -- Social life and customs -- Pictorial works; China -- Social life and customs -- 1949- -- Pictorial works; Great Britain -- Social life and customs -- 20th Century -- Pictorial works; India -- Social life and customs -- Pictorial works; Soviet Union -- Social life and customs -- 1970-1990 -- Pictorial works; United Arab Emirates -- Social life and customs -- Pictorial works; United States -- Social life and customs -- 20th Century -- Pictorial works; Audiocassettes; Audiovisual materials; Black-and-white photographs -- 20th Century; Born digital; Certificates -- 20th Century; Color film (film); Color photographs; Color slides; Contact prints; Electronic documents; Film negatives; Gelatin silver prints; Motion pictures (visual works); Photographic prints -- 20th Century; Photographs -- 20th Century; Posters -- 20th Century; Slides (photographs); Sound recordings -- 20th Century; Storage devices (computer equipment); Videocassettes; Arnold, Eve; Baryshnikov, Mikhail, 1948- -- Portraits; Monroe, Marilyn, 1926-1962 -- Portraits; American Ballet Theatre -- Portraits; Magnum Photos
- June 2003 Acquisition, 1; 25.9; (70 boxes) + 6 rolls + 4 film reels
  General note
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 555
  Arrangement
  Organized under six headings: Papers; Publicity; Photographs; Posters, Prints, and Paintings; Audiovisual Material; Electronic Media
  Scope and Contents
  Boxes 57-59 (sound recordings): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Boxes 60-66 and 204(audiovisual materials): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Boxes 68-71 (motion picture film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Box 72 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Contains correspondence, notes and writings, clippings and tear sheets, diaries, photographs, production materials, sound and video recordings, and computer disks.
  - Papers
    - Eve Arnold letters to Francis Arnold, 1961-1966 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1962-2002; 20 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1961-1996; 16 (Box 2)
    - Diaries, 1963-1993; 3 (Box 2)
    - Bessie Cohen and Cohen family material, 1972-1992; 2 (Box 2)
    - Notebooks relating to book and film projects, undated; 26 (Box 3)
    - Notebooks, diaries, 1979-1987; 14 (Box 4)
    - Notebooks, diaries, 1979, undated; 18 (Box 5)
    - Note cards and exhibition ephemera, 1987-1996; 2 (Box 5)
    - Magnum 40th anniversary, notes and correspondence, 1985-1989; 5 (Box 6)
    - Research notes and writings, undated; 16 (Box 6)
    - Research notes, slides, and writings, undated; 17 (Box 7)
    - Research notes and writings, undated; 2 (Box 8)
    - Index cards for Behind the Veil, undated (Box 9)
    - Index cards for In Retrospect, undated (Box 10)
    - Notes and film scripts, undated; 19 (Box 11)
    - Articles about Eve Arnold, undated (Box 11)
    - Articles by Eve Arnold, undated (Box 11)
    - Text and captions, 1950-1968 (Box 12)
    - Text and captions, 1969-1997 (Box 13)
    - Writings, various drafts, undated (Box 14)
  - Publicity
    - Condition reports for photographs in In Retrospect exhibition, 1996; 3 (Box 15)
    - Auction catalogs; miscellaneous publicity tearsheets and clippings, undated; 18 (Box 15)
    - Publicity binders, undated (Box 16)
    - Publicity binders, undated (Box 17)
    - Publicity binders, undated (Box 18)
    - Publicity binders, undated (Box 19)
    - Spare copies publicity, undated (Box 20)
    - Spare copies publicity, undated (Box 21)
    - Spare copies publicity, undated (Box 22)
    - Tear sheets, Britain, 1961-1963 (Box 23)
    - Tear sheets, Britain, 1964-1966 (Box 24)
    - Tear sheets, Britain, 1967-1968 (Box 25)
    - Tear sheets, Britain, 1970-1979 (Box 26)
    - Tear sheets, Britain, 1977-1992 (Box 27)
    - Tear sheets, Britain, 1992-1997 (Box 28)
    - Tear sheets, United States, 1950-1959 (Box 29)
    - Tear sheets, United States, 1960-1964 (Box 30)
    - Tear sheets, United States, 1967-1984 (Box 31)
    - Tear sheets, other countries including China, undated (Box 32)
    - Tear sheets, other countries including Canada, undated (Box 33)
    - Tear sheets, Russia, undated (Box 34)
    - Tear sheets, Marilyn Monroe and Joan Crawford, undated (Box 35)
    - Published postcards with images by Arnold, undated (Box 36)
  - Photographs
    - Countries
      - Britain, 1961-1964 (Box 37)
      - Britain, 1964-1977 (Box 38)
      - Caribbean - Puerto Rico, undated (Box 39)
      - South Africa - Soviet Union, undated (Box 40)
      - Soviet Union, undated (Box 41)
    - Personalities
      - Marlene Dietrich, undated (Box 41)
      - Clark Gable - Andy Warhol, undated (Box 42)
      - Marilyn Monroe, undated (Box 43)
    - Groups
      - American Ballet Theatre - Black Muslims, undated (Box 44)
    - Film sets
      - Anne of 1,000 Days - A Man for all Seasons, undated (Box 45)
      - Modesty Blaise - Salt 'n Pepper, undated (Box 46)
    - Other
      - Family (Miller Place) - migrant workers, undated (Box 47)
      - Motherhood - wives, undated (Box 48)
      - Miscellaneous, 1953-1979 (Box 49)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 50)
      - Color photos, undated (Box 51 (Oversize))
      - Color photos, undated (Box 52)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 53 (Oversize))
  - Posters, Prints, and Paintings
    - Posters, undated (Box 54 (Oversize))
    - Posters; honorary degrees from St. Andrews and Staffordshire universities, undated (Box 55 (Oversize))
    - Posters, undated (Box 56 (Oversize))
    - Posters, undated (Box 198 (Roll))
    - Poster: Derek Jarman / Eve Arnold exhibition, Barbican, London, 1996 (Box 199 (Roll))
    - Posters, undated (Box 200 (Roll))
    - Posters, undated (Box 201 (Roll))
    - Asian tempera paintings, undated (Box 202 (Roll))
    - Asian prints, undated (Box 203 (Roll))
  - Audiovisual Materials
    Conditions Governing Access
    Boxes 60-66 and 204 (audiovisual materials): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Sound recordings
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Behind the Veil, circa 1971; 26 (Box 57)
        - Roll 1, 1971 April 28; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619276)
          Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
        - Roll 2, 1971 April 28; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619284)
        - Roll 3, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619292)
        - Roll 4, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619300)
        - Roll 5, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619318)
        - Roll 6, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619326)
        - Roll 7, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619334)
        - Roll 8, 1971 May 1; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619342)
        - Roll 9, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619359)
        - Roll 10, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619367)
        - Roll 11, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619375)
        - Roll 12, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619383)
        - Roll 13, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619391)
        - Roll 14, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619409)
        - Roll 15, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619417)
        - Roll 16, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619425)
        - Roll 17, Horse Race / Midday Market / Sewing Machines, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619433)
        - Roll 18, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619441)
        - Roll 19, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619458)
          Content includes interview continued from Roll 18, cloth sellers in desert, camel noises, wind and birds
        - Roll 20, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619466)
        - Roll 21, Midwife and Nurse Interview, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619474)
        - Roll 22, Arabic music 1, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619482)
        - Roll 23, Arabic music 2, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619490)
        - Roll 24, Arabic music 3, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619508)
        - Roll 25, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619516)
        - Roll 26, undated; 1 (Box 57, Item barcode 39002104619524)
      - Behind the Veil, circa 1971; 25 (Box 58)
        - Roll 23, Jack Briggs Interview, A, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619722)
        - Roll 24, Jack Briggs Interview, B, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619730)
        - Roll 27, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619532)
        - Roll 28 A, fish market, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619540)
        - Roll 29, music sync., undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619565)
        - Roll 30, music [?], undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619573)
        - Roll 31, music [?], undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619581)
        - Roll 33, shell harp 1, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619599)
        - Roll 34, shell harp 2, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619607)
        - Roll 35, letter writers, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619615)
        - Roll 36, matchless 1, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619623)
        - Roll 37, matchless 2, coffee grinding, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619631)
        - Roll 38, sheban, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619649)
        - Roll 39, morn singing seq., undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619656)
        - Roll 40, desert / sea / Henry Moore, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619664)
        - Roll 41, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619672)
        - Roll 42, mulla, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619680)
        - Roll 43, Ruth Willis interview, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619771)
        - Eve Arnold "Dubai", one of poetry, 1971 September 4; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619698)
        - Eve Arnold "Dubai", two of poetry; Roll II is best repeats of one and more, 1971 September 4; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619706)
          English and Arabic
        - Tape 2 Voice, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619714)
        - Hini, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619748)
        - John Coles interview, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619755)
        - Chronolog, harem flute, undated; 1 (Box 58, Item barcode 39002104619763)
      - Behind the Veil (4 vinyl recordings) [7- and 10-inch records], undated (Box 59)
        Used in film sound track
      - Behind the Veil (1 tape) [16 mm full-coat magnetic soundtrack], circa 1971 (Box 59)
      - "Magnum Meeting", undated; 1 (Box 59, Item barcode 39002104619086)
      - Miscellaneous interviews and talks
        - 5 Master Photographers; 3. Eve Arnold, Radio 3, 1990 August 28; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619094)
        - Eve Arnold in conversation with Val Williams, 1991 October 22; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619102)
        - Eve Arnold, Dutch Magazine, 1993; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619110)
        - ATM 5-6, Pelvis on Dial; Baseule des jambes, undated; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619128)
        - Interview with Eve Arnold, Kate Buckley, 1990 October 25; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619136)
        - TV interview: Eve Arnold and Eammon McCabe, undated; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619144)
        - Mary Sue Koontz congrats for [?], 1995; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619151)
        - Eve Arnold on B.F.B.S. UK with Annie Nightingale, 1989 October 11; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619169)
        - Eve Arnold: Screen Talk, 2002 July 8; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619177)
          John Tusa, Beeban Kidron, and David Hurn talking about Eve Arnold's work
        - Books & Company, Series 5 - Programme 2, 1997 September; 1; Subject matter includes Eve Arnold's recommendation of six favorite photography books (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619185)
        - John Tusa interview with Eve Arnold, undated; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619193)
        - Eve Arnold interview, WYMS, Maurie Saffarraas, Milwaukee, 1982 July 19; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619201)
        - Martin Bush interviews photojournalist Eve Arnold, 1995 April 28; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619219)
        - Eve Arnold interview with Sarah Sands, 1990 August 2; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619227)
        - Eve Arnold interview, Michael Hallett, 1991 September; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619235)
        - Eve Arnold reading article she wrote about her father, undated; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619243)
        - Eve Arnold interview (1 of 2), 1993 September; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619250)
        - Eve Arnold, WNYC, 1995 November 30; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002104619268)
        - Magnum - Outlook, 1990 March 15; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619789)
        - Artbeat Gill Pyrah with Eve Arnold, Neil Burgess and Tony Collingood, 1990 March 16; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619797)
        - Eve Arnold with Terry Gross - WUHY Philadelphia, undated; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619805)
        - Interview Eve Arnold / Catriona Roberts (BBC ENTS), undated; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619813)
        - WNYC 29B-66-79, 1980; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619821)
        - Eve Arnold / Judy Wenning WNYC, undated; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619839)
        - Interview "In America", 1983 November 29; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619847)
        - Michael's Guitar, Ross Terrill - Tape #2, 1983 December 12; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619854)
        - Eve Arnold / Ross Terrill - Tape #1, 1983 December 12; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619862)
        - Eve Arnold (2 of 2), 1993 September; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619870)
        - Eve Arnold, NPR Weekend Edition, 1987 August 1; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619888)
        - Eve Arnold talks on NY and Company AM 83 of Marilyn Monroe, 1987 August 5; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619896)
        - Jim Eason Show - Eve Arnold, guest, 1983 December 7; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619904)
        - Robert a. Kapp: "Eve Arnold in Perspective", Museum of History and Industry, 1982 February 9; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619912)
        - Interview as a Magnum photog[rapher], Kaleidescope, 1990; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619920)
        - Magnum, "The Way the World Washes" / "The Man with the Gun" (1 of 2), undated; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619938)
        - Magnum at the Millennium, "My Face is Your Fortune" / "Surviving History" / "Cabinet of Curiosity" (2 of 2), undated; 1 (Box 61, Item barcode 39002104619946)
    - Video recordings
      - "Behind the Veil" copy 1 of 3, undated; 1 (Box 62)
      - "Behind the Veil" copy 2 of 3, undated; 1
      - "Behind the Veil" copy 3 of 3, undated; 1
      - "Behind the Veil by Eve Arnold, 1971", YCALMSS611_0007; 1; 00:51:21 (Box 62, Item barcode 39002102349777)
      - "Behind the Veil", undated; YCALMSS611_0008; 1; 00:52:33 (Box 62, Item barcode 39002102349785)
      - "World About US: Behind the Veil Tx: 12/12/71", 1971 December 12; YCALMSS611_0009; 1; 00:50:24; This copy is in fair to poor condition. (Box 62, Item barcode 39002102349793)
      - "Design Classics: World About Us: Behind the Veil", 1990 February 22; YCALMSS611_0010; 1; 00:50:29; This is a poor quality transfer of "Behind the Veil". (Box 62, Item barcode 39002102349801)
      - "Eve Arnold - In Retrospect" by Beeban Kidron for BBC's Omnibus (1 of 2), 1996 March 22; YCALMSS611_0011; 1; 00:53:00 (Box 62, Item barcode 39002102349819)
      - "Eve Arnold - In Retrospect" by Beeban Kidron for BBC's Omnibus (2 of 2), 1996 March 22; YCALMSS611_0012; 1; 00:52:56 (Box 62, Item barcode 39002102349827)
      - "Scene '90; All in a Day's Work publicity", 1990 March; YCALMSS611_0013; 1; 00:25:47 (Box 62, Item barcode 39002102349835)
        Note from HTV West: With compliments and thanks for your help. Please be kind enough to pass the tape to Eve Arnold, with whom I've already spoken.